rif.org 2010-06-20

# Reading Is Fundamental | Privacy Policy

| 

**Reading Is Fundamental, Inc. (hereafter "RIF") is committed to earning and keeping the trust and confidence of our donors.  To that end, RIF1 has established the following practices regarding privacy.**

Thank you for your support of Reading Is Fundamental.  We value the trust you have placed in us. This privacy policy describes the measures we take to protect the personal information of our donors. It also describes our solicitation strategies and the choices you can make about how we use the information you provide to us. At the end of this privacy policy, you will find a link to help you update your preferences and contact information for RIF's development department.

**1\. Protection of Donor  Information **

RIF understands that a donor's or prospective donor's (referred to herein collectively as "Donor") personal information collected through the fundraising process is sensitive. RIF personnel who have access to "Donor Information" (as defined below) are required to sign an internal confidentiality policy, which is reviewed and updated annually, and to acknowledge the ethical policies of the Association of Professional Researchers for Advancement, the Association of Fundraising Professionals, and the Donor Bill of Rights. 

The following practices guide RIF's recordkeeping on donors:

> a.  Access to information in RIF's donor database and paper files containing personal information of donors or prospective donors ("Donor Information") is limited to personnel in the Development Department, other select RIF personnel and certain other non-profit organizations. 
> 
> b.  Electronic and paper documents maintained by RIF and relating primarily to Donor Information will be disposed of when no longer needed. 
> 
> c.  RIF notifies its vendors, consultants, and other third parties of RIF's confidentiality policies before such third parties gain access to Donor Information for purposes of carrying out fundraising activities for RIF. 
> 
> d.  Donors may have reasonably prompt access to their own Donor Information upon written request, but may not view any other records.

All Donor Information is the property of RIF.

**2\. General Solicitation Practices**

It is RIF's standard practice to include all donors in our regular solicitation schedule. Donors and prospective donors may call or e-mail the development staff to advise how often  they wish to be solicited, to not receive solicitations, to not receive any mail at all from RIF, to not receive e-mail, or that their contact information not be shared with other organizations. RIF will do its best to honor any such request.

RIF defines these options as follows:

**_One solicitation per year_ :** A donor or prospective donor will receive a solicitation as part of RIF’s year-end direct mail appeal. Additionally, donors and prospective donors may also receive e-mail communications from RIF if they have provided an e-mail address.

**_Do not solicit_ :** A donor or prospective donor will not receive any solicitations from RIF. A donor will still receive standard acknowledgments when a gift is made, Required Reading (RIF's donor newsletter), and an annual report. 

**_Do not mail_ : **The only mail these donors will receive are acknowledgments from RIF when a gift is made. These donors may, however, continue to receive e-mails. Donors must also request that their record be marked "Do not e-mail" if they do not wish to receive electronic communications.

**_Do not e-mail_ : **For all gifts made online, RIF requires donors to submit their e-mail address. However, donors may choose not to receive communication via e-mail through a check-off box at the end of the online donation form. Checking this box will notify RIF that the donor does not wish to receive RIF’s eNewsletter (unless they have previously subscribed) or any other electronic solicitations. Donors will still receive an automatic electronic acknowledgment for their gift shortly after it is made.

**_Do not share_ : **Although RIF does not sell its mailing or e-mail lists, we may exchange lists with other nonprofit organizations through a recognized list brokerage firm. Any donor may request that their name not be shared with other organizations. Donors will continue to receive mailings, solicitations and general communications from RIF.

In addition, any donor may request to give anonymously. Anonymity means that the donor will be excluded from any annual report or general donation listings. In addition, that individual's record will automatically be marked "Do not share" to ensure that his or her name is excluded should RIF share any of its lists. Anonymous donors will continue to receive solicitations and updates on RIF. 

Please note that RIF reserves the right to contact a donor by whatever means necessary should a problem arise with a gift.

_[_Click here_ ](https://secure2.convio.net/rif/site/SPageServer?pagename=myPage&JServSessionIdr001=fuh0848ms2.app6a)_if you wish to update your preferences or your contact information.

Donor requests:

> a.  Via U.S. Mail: 
>
>> Reading Is Fundamental, Inc.  
> Attn: Development Department  
> 1825 Connecticut Avenue, NW  
> Suite 400  
> Washington, DC 20009-5726 
> 
> b.  Via e-mail: [development@rif.org](mailto:development@rif.org) 
> 
> c.  Via telephone: (888)725-4801

**3\. Website Privacy**

Your privacy is important to RIF and the information below describes RIF's privacy practices for its own website. For information concerning RIF's website privacy practices relating to children, please read Section 3g of this policy.

  1. **Information We Collect and How We Use That Information** :  
Our registration forms require users to give us contact information that may include name, e-mail address, mailing address, interests, and similar information. We do not permanently store sensitive information from our visitors, such as social security or credit card numbers (except in the case of recurring donors whose credit cards are charged on a monthly basis in the amount authorized by the donor). We may use your e-mail address to send you RIF communications, but you may let us know that you do not want to receive such communications from us.

  2. **Internet Protocol Address and Other Aggregate Data** :  
We collect an IP address from all visitors to our site. An IP address is a number that is automatically assigned to your computer when you use the Internet. We use IP addresses to help diagnose problems with our server, administer our site, analyze trends, track users' movement, gather broad demographic information for aggregate use in order for us to improve the site, and deliver customized, personalized content. We do not link IP addresses to personally identifiable information. 

We also automatically collect and store the name of the domain and host from which you access the Internet, the browser software you use, the operating system you use, the date and time you access our site, and the Internet address of the site from which you linked (if any) directly to our site.

We use this information only as anonymous aggregate data to help diagnose problems with our server, administer our site, analyze trends, track user’s movement, and gather broad demographic information in order for us to improve the site, deliver customized, personalized content, and overall make our site more useful.

We do not track or record information about individuals or link this data to personally identifiable information.

  3. **Use of "Cookies"** :   
Our site may use cookies to enhance your experience while using our site. Cookies are pieces of information that some websites transfer to the computer that is browsing that website and are used for recordkeeping and data tracking purposes. Use of cookies makes web surfing easier by performing certain functions such as saving your passwords and your personal preferences regarding your use of the particular website. 

Your browser is probably set to accept cookies. However, if you would prefer not to receive cookies, you can alter the configuration of your browser to refuse cookies. If you choose to have your browser refuse cookies, it is possible that some areas of our site will not function properly when you view them. 

  4. **Security** :  
Information provided to RIF is transmitted using SSL (Secure Socket Layer) encryption. SSL is a coding system that lets your browser automatically encrypt, or scramble, data before you send it to us. We also protect account information by placing it on a secure portion of our site that is designed to be only accessible by certain authorized personnel of RIF. Unfortunately, however, no data transmission over the Internet is 100 percent secure. While we strive to protect your information, we cannot ensure or warrant the security of such information. 

  5. **Tell-A-Friend; e-cards; eNewsletter** :  
If a user elects to use our referral service for informing a friend about our site, we ask them for the friend's name and e-mail address. RIF may then elect to send the friend a one-time e-mail inviting them to visit the site. RIF stores the friend's e-mail address and name and uses this information for the sole purpose of sending this one-time e-mail. 

If a user elects to use our e-card feature to send an electronic greeting card to a friend, we ask them for their name and e-mail address as well as the friend's name and e-mail address. RIF may then send the friend a one-time e-card. RIF stores the sender's and the friend's e-mail address and name and uses this information solely in connection with the e-card feature.

If a user elects to send a back issue of our eNewsletter to a friend, we ask them for the friend's e-mail address. RIF may then send the friend the requested eNewsletter. After sending the eNewsletter, RIF does not store the recipient's e-mail address.

  6. **Other Websites** :  
Our site contains links to other websites. Please note that when you click on one of these links, you are entering another website for which RIF has no responsibility. We encourage you to read the privacy statements on all such sites as their policies may be different than ours.

  7. **Children** :  
The Children's Online Privacy Protection Act ("COPPA") requires that we inform parents and legal guardians about how we collect, use, and disclose personal information from children under 13 years of age; and that we obtain the consent of parents and guardians in order for children under 13 years of age to use certain features of our websites. Below we explain how we do that for these "children." Also, when we use the term "parent" below, we mean to include legal guardians. 

Children can surf RIF.org and view content without any personal information being collected. We collect personal information from children when they register in connection with RIF.org's "Reading Planet Club" and such registration requires parental consent. The only information we collect from children during our registration process is a child's first name, parent's e-mail address, child's birth date, member name, and password. We collect birth dates to validate the ages of our guests, including children. We do not collect any other personally identifiable information from children during our registration process. We may, however, collect a child's e-mail address to respond to specific requests made by a child (e.g., sending the child a birthday e-card or updates to our website or an electronic newsletter). 

In addition, personal information regarding a child may be collected in the course of a child's participation in certain interactive features such as building a personal web page. Following a child's registration (with parental consent) with the "Reading Planet Club," we might collect information concerning, among other things, a child's: favorite book, favorite author, favorite animal, favorite hobby and similar interests. A child who registers with the Reading Planet Club may establish a personal web page that he or she can send to specific friends but that web page may not otherwise be viewed by the public and is not disclosed to other third parties. Note that all websites that are directed to children under 13 are prohibited by law from conditioning a child's participation in an online activity on the child's providing more personal information than is reasonably necessary.

Without parental notice and consent, we do not share any information about a child with any third parties unless the disclosure is reasonably necessary: to comply with law, including, for example, to comply with a court order or subpoena; to enforce our site or game rules; or to protect the safety and security of our guests and our websites. 

Before a child enters a game or contest where he or she may win a prize, we first contact the child's parent at the e-mail address provided to us and seek parental consent for participation in the contest. If a child wins a game or contest, we notify the parent at the parent's e-mail address. We may publish a winner's first name, city, and state of residence on our website. In certain instances a prize may be sent to a game or contest winner by a third party corporate sponsor of RIF. In those instances, we will give to such third party the name and mailing address of the winner solely to facilitate the shipment of the prize. Any such third party corporate sponsor will not permanently store the name and mailing address of a winner and will not use that information for any other purposes. 

As described above in Section 3(c), the "Reading Planet" portion of our web site also uses cookies.

At any time parents can refuse to permit us to collect further personal information from their child and can request that any personal information we have collected be deleted from our records. Parents can also access the personal information we have collected. To make such a request, a parent must send an e-mail to [kids@rif.org](mailto:kids@rif.org). Please include the child's member name and the parent's e-mail address in the e-mail so that we can better assist you with your inquiry or request.

We may amend our Privacy Policy at any time. We will provide parents notice by e-mail of any material changes in the way we intend to collect, use, and/or share children’s personal information and will make changes in accordance with COPPA. Please note that, at all times, parents should update their personal information to provide us current e-mail addresses.

If you have questions or concerns about our Privacy Policy as it pertains to children please e-mail us at [kids@rif.org](mailto:kids@rif.org) or contact us via regular mail at Reading Is Fundamental, Inc., Attention RIF Online Team, 1825 Connecticut Avenue, NW, Suite 400, Washington, DC 20009 or call us at 1 (877) RIF-READ or (202) 536-3400. 

  8. **Changes to Policy and Contact Information** :  
Except as set forth in the portion of this policy concerning the collection of personal information of children (Section g), RIF reserves the right, at any time and without notice, to modify this policy by simply posting such changes on our website. Any modifications will be effective immediately upon posting. If you have any questions or comments about this policy, want to review your personal information collected by RIF, or wish to inform us of your solicitation preferences as stated in Section 2, please contact us through any of the following communication channels: 

Website requests:

> Via U.S. Mail:

> > Reading Is Fundamental, Inc.  
> Attn: Web Team - Privacy Policy  
> 1825 Connecticut Avenue, NW  
> Suite 400  
> Washington, DC 20009-5726 
> 
> Via e-mail: [feedback@rif.org](mailto:feedback@rif.org)

1Please note: the procedures set forth in this policy apply only to Reading Is Fundamental, Inc. Any contact with local RIF programs is guided by their established procedures.
